<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sixteen reasons drawn from the law of God, the law of England, and right reason, to shew why diverse true Christians (called Quakers) refuse to swear at all for the satisfaction of all the upright in heart, that the innocent may not be condemned with the wicked / by John Crook.</title>
            <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1138</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11781073</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11781073</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 812:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sixteen reasons drawn from the law of God, the law of England, and right reason, to shew why diverse true Christians (called Quakers) refuse to swear at all for the satisfaction of all the upright in heart, that the innocent may not be condemned with the wicked / by John Crook.</title>
                  <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  Biblical teaching.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49059:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SIXTEEN REASONS Drawn from the Law of God, THE Law of England, AND Right Reaſon, TO SHEW Why diverſe true Chriſtians (called <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS</hi>) refuſe to Swear at All: For the ſatisfaction of all the Upright in Heart, that the Innocent may not be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the Wicked.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Crook.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Wind-mill</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49059:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49059:2"/>
            <p n="1">I.</p>
            <p>BEcauſe Chriſt Jeſus the KING and LAW-GIVER to his people hath ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> Mat. 5. And it is left upon record for our practiſe, and is ſo ſure that no averment lies good againſt it; which doctrine was practiced before the Apoſtacy, and promoted by the Apoſtles in their day, as may be ſeen, <hi>James</hi> the 5. which may ſerve for an anſwer <hi>(in this caſe)</hi> unto them that plead for ſwearing, as Chriſt ſaid upon another occaſion, which was permitted <hi>in the old time</hi> of the law, but was not ſo from the beginning; ſo Chriſt the Truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deems his children out of the fall, and all that have come in by it unto himſelf, who hath commanded his followers <hi>not to ſwear at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Becauſe <hi>in the Old time,</hi> when ſwearing was uſed according to God's command, expreſſed in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and alſo inſtanced by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a Jew, and wrote unto the Jews, unto whom he ſignified in his Epiſtle, both <hi>the end</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> of ſwearing in thoſe times and caſes wherein it was uſed; who knew very well what was <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Tipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> and what was <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Perpetual,</hi> and therefore mentioneth an Oath in his Epiſtle aforeſaid by way <hi>of figure</hi> and <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> which he inſtanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the particular practice of it at that time, ſaying, <hi>An Oath for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is to them the end of all ſtrife:</hi> and ſo Chriſt, <hi>Gods Oath</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> (the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>all ſhadows</hi> and <hi>figures</hi>) puts an end to all ſtrife and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance between God and that man, which takes hold of Chriſt, and receives him into the heart by the living ſaith, whereby he hath ſtrong conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle, whoſe end in mentioning ſwearing in that 6. of <hi>Heb.</hi> is only by way <hi>of alluſion</hi> and <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> and proves no more a neceſſity of the lawfulneſs or continuance <hi>of ſwearing</hi> (becauſe he mentions the word Oath) then mens living <hi>in ſtrife</hi> proves the lawfulneſs or neceſſity <hi>of the continuance of ſtrife,</hi> becauſe in the ſame place he mentions the word <hi>ſtrife</hi> alſo; the which, if it ſhould be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from his words, would make the Apoſtle a Tranſgreſſor, and guilty of building again the thing that he deſtroyed in his Epiſtle, elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, who concluded the <hi>Corinthians</hi> as <hi>Carnal,</hi> and that not only becauſe they walked <hi>as men,</hi> (which he blames them for) but alſo becauſe they lived <hi>in ſtrife</hi> and <hi>envyings,</hi> &amp;c. So that all which the forementioned place <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. proves, is, only this, that when an Oath was uſed in old time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> according to Gods appointment, it was in thoſe caſes which would put an end <hi>to ſtrife;</hi> and ſo is of authority ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all Oaths now, that are either uſed where there is <hi>no ſtrife at all,</hi> or elſe in thoſe caſes wherein <hi>Oaths are taken,</hi> and <hi>the ſtrife not ended,</hi> which if obſerved, the Oath of Obedience cannot juſtly be required.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Becauſe when ſwearing was in uſe as aforeſaid, we never read in holy writ, that any of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were either made <hi>by an oath,</hi> or required <hi>an oath</hi> of thoſe people that were to be ſubject to them; neither was it required <hi>(upon ſuch a penalty as now it is)</hi> either by the <hi>Common Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Law of England,</hi> untill KING <hi>James</hi> his time, upon occaſion <hi>of the Gun-powder Plot;</hi> which OATH was made <hi>by the</hi> PARLIAMENT, as the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49059:3"/>expedient <hi>(in that juncture of time)</hi> to prevent like deſignes, and alſo to find out the POPES <hi>Alliances</hi> and <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> in theſe Kingdoms; as may be ſeen both by the <hi>Preambles</hi> to the Statutes, and alſo by the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>contents</hi> of the ſaid Oath; and not at all intending thoſe that are <hi>True Proteſtants,</hi> who were not tainted with that curſed <hi>Popiſh Principle</hi> of <hi>breaking faith with an Heretick,</hi> and <hi>depoſing excommunicated</hi> PRINCES, as may be ſeen by the Statute aforeſaid, much leſs thoſe who could not ſwear at all in conſcience to an Oath, becauſe Chriſt hath forbid it.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Becauſe God commands <hi>Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to Magiſtracy, and all his commands are equally to be obſerved; for the breach <hi>of one</hi> renders a man guilty <hi>of all:</hi> and how a Magiſtrate can (in juſtice and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) ſwear men to the obſervance of one command, more than to all the reſt (without partiallity) doth not <hi>to good conſcience</hi> and <hi>right reaſon appear,</hi> except the honour and ſafety of Rulers, ſhould be preferred before the glory of God.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Becauſe <hi>the Ruler</hi>-profeſſing <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and his <hi>Subjects</hi> alſo profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>the ſame,</hi> it ought not to be ſuppoſed that that God (whom the true Chriſtians worſhip) who hath by an inſtinct in nature obliged relations ſo firmly, that he hath never required any other ſecurity for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof, than that bond which he himſelf hath made; And would it not be accounted <hi>prepoſterous</hi> and <hi>abſurd</hi> for <hi>to ſwear a Child to his Father,</hi> or a <hi>Wife</hi> (upon marriage) <hi>to her husband;</hi> and is it any whit leſs abſurd and needleſs <hi>to ſwear</hi> a true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſubject to <hi>a Chriſtian King?</hi> ſeeing the Command of God no leſs requires Obedience to him, then to the other relations; and doth not this promiſe as much, or more belong to him that rules for God, as to any particular Chriſtian, <hi>viz.</hi> Who ſhall harm you, if you follow that which is good? And will not God puniſh Rebellion as the ſin of witchcraft, which is ſecurity ſufficient for <hi>a Chriſtian Prince?</hi> and therefore ought not to impoſe an Oath upon them, who cannot ſwear for conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Becauſe <hi>an oath,</hi> in this caſe, hath been found by experience to be inſufficient, as to anſwer the end for which it is given; and therefore, for the refuſing of it <hi>(by true Chriſtians as aforeſaid, or thoſe that cannot ſwear at all)</hi> ought not to make them liable to the penalty of the Statute; and to prove that it is not able to anſwer the end aforeſaid: witneſs all thoſe at any time, who have been found in rebellion againſt the King, who have they been <hi>but the Swearers,</hi> and <hi>Lyars,</hi> and <hi>Covenant breakers?</hi> ſo that their Oaths have been of no more uſe to them, than to beget a perſwaſion in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that now their Prince is ſatisfied concerning their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and they may plot with leſſe ſuſpition; and ſo with <hi>Judas</hi> will cry, <hi>Hail Maſter,</hi> and <hi>kiſs Him,</hi> that they may get <hi>their Rewards,</hi> and bring <hi>their Deſignes</hi> to paſs.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Becauſe he that ſwears, is either <hi>a True man,</hi> or <hi>a falſe;</hi> if <hi>a True man,</hi> his Honeſty without an Oath, engageth him <hi>to performance;</hi> but if <hi>a falſe man,</hi> he will <hi>ſwear,</hi> rather than forfeit <hi>his Liberty</hi> and <hi>Eſtate;</hi> and ſo his Oath doth <hi>but ſave himſelf,</hi> but is no <hi>ſecurity to the King;</hi> and it may eaſily be ſuppoſed, that he that will ſwear for his own advantage, <hi>only,</hi> will not refuſe <hi>to plot,</hi> when he may <hi>do it,</hi> as he thinketh, for his own preferment,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49059:3"/>eſpecially conſidering, he that ſwears <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and yet proves <hi>a Traitor,</hi> is no more puniſhed, then he that <hi>commits Treaſon,</hi> and <hi>ſwears not at all;</hi> and therefore ſeeing SWEARING cannot bind <hi>a Knave,</hi> and GOODNESSE will bind <hi>an honeſt man,</hi> what ſound reaſon then can be given, why the <hi>good man</hi> ſhould be ſo ſeverely puniſhed, onely, becauſe <hi>he cannot ſwear at all?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Becauſe the OATH <hi>of Judges</hi> and <hi>Juſtices,</hi> which is to do equall Law and Execution of right to all <hi>the Kings loving Subjects;</hi> which Oath is not obſerved, except the Judge diſtinguiſh, and put a difference between them, who only refuſe to ſwear, <hi>becauſe all Oaths are forbidden,</hi> and thoſe who refuſe to ſwear <hi>becauſe Allegiance is required;</hi> for the one likes not the thing <hi>ſworn to,</hi> and the others owns the thing, <hi>but denies the Oath;</hi> and to puniſh him that denies to ſwear in the one ſence, equally with him, who refuſeth to ſwear in the other ſence, is neither execution of equal law, nor right, and ſo not according to their Oaths aforeſaid,.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Becauſe that the Kings ſafety depends, not <hi>upon ſwearing,</hi> but upon <hi>performing</hi> the thing to which the Oath is required, and if that <hi>be given,</hi> or <hi>yeilded,</hi> the end is anſwered, though there be <hi>no ſwearing at all;</hi> and therefore the penalty for not taking the Oath, ought not to be impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, who refuſe to ſwear in conſcience to an Oath, eſpecially conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Law hath provided <hi>another penalty</hi> for them, as in caſes <hi>of high Treaſon,</hi> if guilty thereof; and to require <hi>two ſecurities</hi> for one debt, ſeemes to be <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> and is <hi>no leſſe abſurd,</hi> than for a man, who hath <hi>a juſt debt</hi> owing unto him upon a bond, which debt <hi>is proffered to be paid</hi> according to the contents of the bond, but will not be received <hi>(by the Creditor)</hi> except the perſon will firſt SWEAR <hi>to perform the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. Becauſe to puniſh ſo ſeverely, as <hi>to the loſs of Liberty</hi> and <hi>Eſtate</hi> for the refuſall of <hi>a Ceremony</hi> (as it is called by the impoſers thereof) and that denyed out of conſcience to Chriſts command, is contrary both to <hi>the nature</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of the law, which is <hi>to puniſh for offences;</hi> and therefore to ſtand upon the <hi>Letter</hi> or <hi>Ceremony,</hi> when <hi>the Truth</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is anſwered, is to make the Law <hi>become cruell,</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>deſtroy,</hi> and not mercifull <hi>to ſave;</hi> which is all one, as if a man ſhould ſay, <hi>the Sun was only to</hi> ſcorch <hi>and</hi> burn, <hi>and not to</hi> warm <hi>nor give</hi> light; and as if <hi>the earth</hi> ſhould be ſaid only <hi>to bury,</hi> and <hi>not to bring forth encreaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">XI. Becauſe it hath been obſerved, by Statutes, as in the Stat. of the firſt of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> that <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honeſty</hi> binds ſtronger <hi>to Kings</hi> and <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> than the <hi>ſeverity</hi> of Laws, made with extream <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>rigorous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments,</hi> for not obeying their <hi>Soveraign, Ruler</hi> and <hi>Governour,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore <hi>the Oath of Obedience,</hi> which was made <hi>by the</hi> PARLIAMENT (as in anger and haſt) againſt <hi>the Papiſts,</hi> being provoked thereunto <hi>by the Gunpowder Plot,</hi> the occaſion of making that Statute, &amp;c. And therefore ought not <hi>(in the coole of the day)</hi> to be ſtood upon according to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of it, the ſubſtance being kept to: Beſides, in the third part of COOK'S <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> cap. 74. he ſaith, <hi>That there were certain poor</hi> Chriſtians <hi>That had ſpoken againſt the worſhipping</hi> of Images, <hi>In Juſtification of Gods Command</hi> (as many <hi>do now</hi> againſt <hi>ſwearing at all,</hi> becauſe Chriſt hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid it) yet notwithſtanding, <hi>then</hi> as <hi>now,</hi> thoſe poor Chriſtians were by the Biſhops of that time, <hi>ſworn to worſhip</hi> Images; <hi>which</hi> OATH, ſaith
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49059:4"/>Cook, <hi>was againſt the expreſs Command of God,</hi> (and therefore ought not to have been impoſed) <hi>And the Law of the Nation, becauſe they had no warrant to miniſter the ſame.</hi> And if <hi>this</hi> was condemned <hi>in that day,</hi> and that by the <hi>Chief Juſtice of</hi> ENGLAND (who alſo is called the Oracle of the Law) it may well be hoped, that the like evill practiſe will not be juſtified <hi>in this time</hi> of greater light; although ſome plead <hi>for ſwearing</hi> NOW a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chriſt's c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmand,</hi> as ſome did <hi>THEN</hi> for the worſhipping of Images gainſt <hi>Gods Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">XII. Becauſe, <hi>to take away</hi> mens <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>ſwear at all,</hi> cannot be drawn into example for others, except to teach them <hi>to ſwear,</hi> which they are apt enough to do without exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for the Rule of the Law is, <hi>Paena ad paucos ut motus ad omnes perveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at; The puniſhment is to a few, that all may fear;</hi> which is not obſerved in this caſe, becauſe the puniſhment for refuſing <hi>to ſwear at all,</hi> cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an example <hi>to deter men</hi> from committing <hi>of Treaſon;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the penalty aforeſaid, ought not to be inflicted, as in the caſe of <hi>Cook's</hi> 3d part of <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> where he mentions a man committing <hi>Treaſon, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he prove not</hi> Sanae Memoriae, <hi>he ſhall not be called to anſwer;</hi> or <hi>if after judgement he becomes ſo, he ſhall not be executed:</hi> and the reaſon given by <hi>COOK,</hi> is, <hi>becauſe it cannot be an example to others;</hi> which reaſon is much more true in the caſe in hand.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Becauſe it was <hi>a Brand</hi> upon <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat, that he cauſed</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſin,</hi> which he did, by cauſing them to worſhip the <hi>Calves,</hi> at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> which he had ſet up, though under a plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible pretence <hi>(as may be ſeen by the ſtory)</hi> yet notwithſtanding their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying his command, this thing was their <hi>ſin:</hi> So in like manner would it be ſin now in them, who <hi>cannot ſwear at all,</hi> becauſe Chriſt hath commanded ſo, if they ſhould take the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> or <hi>any other Oath</hi> which he hath forbidden.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Becauſe the proceedings of the Miniſters of the Law, are, and have been <hi>more Irregular</hi> in their apprehending and ſecuring of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons unto whom they tender the <hi>Oaths, than their denial</hi> to take the <hi>Oaths</hi> may be deemed to be; becauſe the <hi>former</hi> is againſt the very fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Lawes of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> with ſeveral other Lawes, that are expreſly againſt <hi>the ſearching of mens houſes, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their perſons by Souldiers or Armed men, in the times of peace;</hi> as alſo is ſignified by the Kings <hi>late Proclamation,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>That for the future, ſuch things ſhall not be practiſed; and if any do, they ſhall incur his diſpleaſure, and be proceeded againſt according to Law;</hi> which is ſuch an <hi>implication</hi> as amounts to an <hi>affirmation,</hi> that what hath been done hitherto in that kind, <hi>is contrary to Law;</hi> beſides <hi>an errour in the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> is of more danger <hi>then in any other part of the building:</hi> but the latter (which are thoſe that deny to take the <hi>Oath</hi>) is only againſt a law made in haſt or anger, as aforeſaid, and but againſt the <hi>Ceremony</hi> or <hi>forma verbalis,</hi> and not againſt <hi>forma legalis</hi> or <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the ſaid Law; and therefore by <hi>lex talionis,</hi> may by many degrees be better diſpenced withall than the former.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. Becauſe of the many differing judgements about Chriſts words, <hi>(ſwear not at all)</hi> which Miniſters a ſtrong ground of ſuſpition, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49059:4"/>there is a <hi>confederacy</hi> among, and between thoſe, who agree like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> to deſtroy Chriſts words from being a command to forbid all ſwearing; and yet fall out about their opinions, when they come to get fairly rid of his words; for one ſaith, that <hi>Chriſts Words</hi> (not at all) <hi>are meant not ſwearing in ordinary communication, and ſo only extend to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid profane and common ſwearing;</hi> which cannot be Chriſts intention, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was forbidded in old time, as appeareth both by two inſtances, he nameth himſelf, as neither to <hi>forſwear themſelves,</hi> nor <hi>to ſwear, and not perform;</hi> and alſo when it was ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain:</hi> But Chriſts words forbid that that was not forbidden in old time, as may be ſeen by the Anallegy of the place, <hi>(but I ſay unto you,</hi> &amp;c.)</p>
            <p>Others they find fault with the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſay it may rather ſignify <hi>commonly, frequently, altogether, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo do not only blemiſh the Diſciples of Chriſt, to whom he ſpake thoſe words, as if they ſhould be <hi>common</hi> or <hi>frequent ſwearers,</hi> but alſo caſt dirt upon Chriſt himſelf, as if he would allow his diſciples, or connive <hi>at their ſwearing</hi> ſometimes <hi>in their communication,</hi> ſo they do it but <hi>ſeldom,</hi> or <hi>now</hi> and <hi>than,</hi> and not <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together,</hi> or <hi>commonly,</hi> and <hi>frequently:</hi> And ſo would rather expoſe Chriſt to be cenſured for his conniving at his diſciples ſwearing <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times</hi> in their Communication, if they do it <hi>not commonly, &amp;c.</hi> then let the word <hi>(not at all)</hi> ſtand, though it better anſwers the Objectors ſenſe, then any of his forced meanings; but then all <hi>ſwearing</hi> muſt be forbidden, which is a doctrine hard to be practiſed in ſuffering times, by thoſe who love their eaſe, more than Chriſt; or elſe ſuch might have known, that a mean Grecian may know that the word is tranſlated right enough, and hath been ſo adjudged (by them who love <hi>ſwearing</hi> as well as this <hi>Objector</hi>) and better ſaves the Anallegy of the Text, then any of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſes; and it will be hard for the <hi>Objector</hi> to find <hi>a Greek Word</hi> that ſo properly ſignifies, <hi>not at all,</hi> as the word in the <hi>Text:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Chriſts words, <hi>not at all,</hi> may better ſtand than <hi>theirs,</hi> who have a mind to <hi>ſwear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others ſay by his words, <hi>not at all,</hi> are meant <hi>not ſwearing at all, by any creature, as the hair of the Head,</hi> or <hi>Temple,</hi> &amp;c. But it is no more true than the former, becauſe that <hi>Oath</hi> alſo was condemned in the old time, for they were to ſwear only <hi>by the living God:</hi> beſides, <hi>He that ſwears by the Temple, ſwears by him that dwells therein,</hi> as ſaith Chriſt elſewhere; but if this meaning were true, the <hi>Oath</hi> they plead for would be made void, which is <hi>by</hi> or upon <hi>a book,</hi> which is made of creatures, as <hi>paper,</hi> and <hi>ink,</hi> and <hi>leather,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>by</hi> or <hi>upon</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> (according to their <hi>Oath) who were men and creatures:</hi> and ſo according to this interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch make themſelves tranſgreſſors, by building again by their <hi>pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe</hi> what they deſtroyed <hi>by their Opinions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others ſay, by not Swearing, <hi>at All,</hi> is meant <hi>onely in the Church;</hi> but we may ſwear, <hi>when called to it by Rulers of the world,</hi> &amp;c. and this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as falſe as the reſt, and theſe cannot clear themſelves from a conſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with them, to deſtroy Chriſt's Doctrine; becauſe that <hi>which is an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in the Church, or in a corner,</hi> is aggravated, <hi>by being committed in the world, as upon the houſe, top.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49059:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Others ſay, by not ſwearing <hi>at all,</hi> is meant, <hi>only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ncerning Chriſts condemning the falſe gloſſes, and ſayings of the Phariſees, and not intended by him to ſtraiten ſwearing from what it was in the old time:</hi> But this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation will not excuſe theſe from a conſederacy, withall the former, to deſtroy the ſimplicity of Chriſt's doctrine; for it is evident by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, that them of old time were the true Prophets and Servants of the Lord, as may be ſeen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. ver. 21. where it is ſaid <hi>by them of old time,</hi> the Greek is, <hi>to them of old time,</hi> as may be ſeen upon the Margent of the Bibles, and ſo plainly intends thoſe, to whom God ſpake, which was <hi>Moſes</hi> and the true Prophets, not the falſe, as theſe confederates would make them: beſides all theſe following inſtances which Chriſt mentions, being Gods commands given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> one of Gods commands, but now is ſtraitued by Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>He that is angry with his brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And Verſe 27. where another Command ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery;</hi> which is alſo ſtraitned by Chriſt in theſe words, <hi>But I ſay unto you, whoſoever looketh upon a Woman, to luſt after her, &amp;c.</hi> which other inſtances he gives, no more Phariſaical than theſe: by all which we may ſee the ſeveral exceptions named by Chriſt, and not left to mans will, <hi>viz.</hi> where the exception to be angry, is, <hi>without a cauſe;</hi> and the exception to the looking upon a woman, is, <hi>to luſt after her;</hi> and the exception con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Divorce, is, <hi>ſaving for the cauſe of fornication.</hi> And therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all theſe caſes the particular Exceptions are named, it may not be ſuppoſed, that he would have omitted it in the caſe of Swearing, if he had intended <hi>any at all.</hi> And therefore theſe Confederates thus differing in their Judgements, it may be eaſily concluded by a wiſe man, That there is more cauſe than bare ſuſpition, that theſe are agreed, and reſolved, to fruſtrate Chriſt's Command, whatſoever the conſequences be: And therefore it is neither <hi>Reaſon</hi> nor <hi>Equity,</hi> that the Innocent ſhould ſuffer by reaſon of the Confederates aforeſaid; or have <hi>their Liberties</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> taken away from them, becauſe they are bold to aſſert <hi>Chriſts Doctrine,</hi> and dare not break <hi>his Commands,</hi> nor follow <hi>a multitude</hi> to do evill.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. Becauſe although <hi>Swearing</hi> were lawfull <hi>in ſome caſes</hi> that are <hi>juſt,</hi> yet it doth not follow, that a man may lawfully <hi>Swear</hi> to every thing <hi>that a Magiſtrate requires an Oath;</hi> for that were to give him a liberty not only to call <hi>that juſt,</hi> which to him <hi>ſeemeth ſo;</hi> but alſo <hi>to affix an Oath unto it,</hi> which both layes a ſnare before the Magiſtrate, of his being <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> and alſo of the Subjects being <hi>in danger of ſlavery:</hi> and therefore it is both equal and juſt, that thoſe who plead for, and require Swearing, (upon great penalties) ſhould be limited unto thoſe preſidents and caſes in the Scriptures, which they themſelves bring to prove the ſame, or elſe to ceaſe the impoſing thereof, leſt they thereby become guilty of Chriſts Charge, <hi>by not onely breaking his Command themſelves, but forcing others ſo to do.</hi> And therefore if an Oath be required in thoſe caſes, for which we have neither <hi>Preſident</hi> nor <hi>Example,</hi> (from that LAW-GIVER which is only able <hi>to ſave,</hi> and <hi>to deſtroy</hi>) the Refuſers thereof, ought not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled <hi>by Pains</hi> and <hi>Penalties,</hi> leſt thoſe be grieved, for whom Chriſt died, and the Magiſtrate take upon him to make that Juſt and Good, <hi>by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> which is not ſo <hi>in it ſelf:</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
